All right, בוקר טוב, Boker tov,
בוקר טוב. Boker tov. Today's דף daf is כ"ה, Kaf Hey, 25,
and we pick up about
a little bit into it already. We pick up about ובתרומה דאורייתא
לא אכל. Uvitruma de'oraita lo achal. It's right alongside the words עזרא
ב Ezra Bet in the margins, about 10 lines down. So basically,
the question here is on what basis can you assume that if
somebody is either doing the נשיאת כפיים, nesi'at kapayim, דוכנינג, duchening, or
eating תרומה, terumah, if they say one word about eating תרומה, terumah,
that you on that basis is that good enough evidence that if
he's doing that and doing that in public and the ציבור tzibur
is allowing that to be done and so on, that a presumption
that he's a good enough evidence that he's a כהן kohen even
for יוחסין yuchsin purposes, for marriage purposes? So that's the question that's
at hand. I should say something that תוספות Tosafot points out that
the issue about תרומה terumah is not a question of eating תרומה,
terumah, although the גמרא Gemara made it sound like that because it
says well, תרומה terumah you eat it in private, so maybe it's
not such a proof. But תוספות Tosafot actually says by other גמרות
Gemarot it's quite clear that the issue by תרומה terumah is the
fact that he is תרומה terumah is distributed to him when he
goes to the, you know, when he goes to the threshing floor
and so on, and we're going to see that coming up later
as well. So just an important point about a nuance about that.
And part of the issue actually that תוספות Tosafot says that relates
to the question about can תרומה terumah be an inference that he's
a כהן kohen for other purposes is also the issue about that
an עבד eved can eat תרומה terumah as well and maybe the
כהן kohen sent his עבד, eved, sent his slave to the threshing
floor, so that's also a factor in this issue. Anyway, the גמרא
Gemara now is specifically focusing on the question about exactly that. Can
דוכנינג duchening or eating תרומה terumah be evidence? And it brings the
story from עזרא Ezra where it says that these family of כהנים
kohanim since they could not prove their exact lineage, it was told
that they cannot eat from קודש הקדשים, kodesh hakodashim, the Holy of
Holies. And the ברייתא baraita on this says that they could still
continue to eat תרומה, terumah, they just couldn't eat קדשים. kodshim. And
the גמרא Gemara therefore, and presumably also as the גמרא Gemara said
yesterday, they were also doing דוכנינג. duchening. So they were doing the
things that they used to do in the exile. So why are
we not going to learn from that that they can go ahead
and not,
I mean, so from there clearly it's true that we would say
that you cannot infer from that תרומה terumah for יוחסין yuchsin because
the whole point was to keep them on the sort of out
status? And the גמרא Gemara said that was a special case, that
even though maybe normally you could infer from תרומה terumah or נשיאת
כפיים nesi'at kapayim to יוחסין, yuchsin, here the question had already been
raised, there was already a stigma, we're not concerned. Okay, so that
was that. But then that other point of that ברייתא baraita was
to tell you how powerful החזקה hachazaka is. That since they had
been doing it in the exile, they could continue doing it now
that they were back in ישראל. Yisrael. So what's the חידוש chiddush
of the החזקה? hachazaka? Like, of course, why not? So one answer
the גמרא Gemara was that before they were eating only תרומה דרבנן
teruma derabbanan and now they're eating תרומה דאורייתא, teruma de'oraita, and that
we're going to let them eat תרומה דאורייתא, teruma de'oraita, and the
other is no, no, no, even now we're only going to let
them eat תרומה דרבנן, teruma derabbanan, but the חידוש chiddush is is
that there's more things to be concerned about eating תרומה דרבנן teruma
derabbanan in ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael and we're not going to be
concerned. Okay, so that's this question about this family of כהנים. kohanim.
They were eating תרומה דרבנן teruma derabbanan in חוץ לארץ. Chutz La'aretz.
Were they now going to start eating תרומה דאורייתא teruma de'oraita in
ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael given the questions that were raised? So now
the גמרא Gemara says like this. ובתרומה דאורייתא לא אכל? Uvitruma de'oraita
lo achal? So according to the possibility that even when they got
to ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael they were only going to eat תרומה
דרבנן teruma derabbanan because of the questions that had been raised, are
you really telling me that they could not eat תרומה דאורייתא? teruma
de'oraita? והכתיב, Vehakativ, the verse says אשר לא יאכל מקודש הקדשים. Asher
lo yochel mikodesh hakodashim.
This is the verse we quoted yesterday. They can't eat from the
Holy of Holies, the most holy things. So מקודש הקדשים הוא דלא
יאכל, Mikodesh hakodashim hu d'lo yochel, from the holy things, presumably like
the קדשים, kodshim, הא בתרומה דאורייתא אכל, ha bitruma de'oraita achal, but
other things, even if they're biblical like תרומה דאורייתא, teruma de'oraita, אכל,
achal, they could eat.
So how could you tell me that they couldn't eat the תרומה
דאורייתא? teruma de'oraita? No. הכי קאמר. Hachi ka'amar.
I don't know.
הכי קאמר. Hachi ka'amar. Look. לא במידי דאיקרי קודש, Lo bemidi dikri
kodesh, they wouldn't eat things that are called קודש. kodesh. דכתיב, Dechtiv,
וכל זר לא יאכל קודש. Vechol zar lo yochal kodesh.
Any in- foreign non-כהן kohen cannot eat קודש kodesh and that's referring
to תרומה terumah in the context. ולא במידי דאיקרי קדשים, V'lo bemidi
dikri kodshim, and not
things that are called קדשים. kodshim. דכתיב ובת כהן כי תהיה לאיש
זר היא בתרומת הקדשים לא תאכל. Dechtiv uvat kohen ki tiheyeh le'ish
zar hi bitrumat hakodashim lo tochel. And when a daughter of a
כהן kohen is married to somebody else, היא בתרומת הקדשים לא תאכל.
hi bitrumat hakodashim lo tochel. So what does בתרומת הקדשים bitrumat hakodashim
mean? It doesn't sound like standard תרומה. terumah. So what does it
mean? So the גמרא Gemara says ואמר מר, v'amar mar, and we
teach, במורם מן הקדשים לא תאכל. bimuram min hakodashim lo tochel.
The thing that is lifted up from the קדשים. kodshim. What does
that mean? It means that the כהן kohen is given the חזה
ושוק chazeh v'shok of the שלמים, shelamim, the breast and the thigh
of the שלמים. shelamim. That's מורם, muram, right? It says שוק התרומה
וחזה התנופה. shok haterumah v'chazeh hatenufa.
It's called explicitly in the תורה Torah תרומה, terumah, lifted up, heave
offering as the English says.
And that's going to be eaten by the כהנים kohanim and not
just by the כהנים kohanim but their whole family, by their slaves
and by their wives and so on like תרומה. terumah. Okay. Now
the interesting הלכה halacha though here is is that if a בת
כהן... bat kohen... And by their daughters, if a daughter of a
כהן kohen marries a non-כהן, kohen, she stops eating תרומה, terumah, she
stops eating this portion of the קדשים, kodshim, then her ישראל Yisrael
husband dies, leaves her without children, she takes care of יבום yibum
and חליצה, chalitza, whatever. Anyway, then she goes back to her כהן
kohen family, right, because she has no longer any tie to the
ישראל Yisrael tribe there. So therefore, and she goes back to eating
תרומה. terumah. But the interesting הלכה halakha is, is that if a
בת כהן, bat kohen, and by their daughters, if a daughter of
a כהן kohen marries a non-כהן, kohen, she stops eating תרומה, terumah,
she stops eating this portion of the קדשים, kodshim, then her ישראל
Yisrael husband dies, leaves her without children, she takes care of יבום
yibum and חליצה, chalitza, whatever. Anyway, then she goes back to her
כהן kohen family, right, because she has no longer any tie to
the ישראל Yisrael tribe there. So therefore, and she goes back to
eating תרומה. terumah. But the interesting הלכה halakha is, she goes back
to eating תרומה, terumah, but she does not go back to eating
this portion of the קרבנות. korbanot. That's the דרשה drasha on this
פסוק. pasuk. It's not clear from this גמרא, gemara, but רש"י Rashi
brings it in from another גמרא. gemara. It says, once she was
to an איש זר, ish zar, to a ישראל, Yisrael, she can
no longer, even if the guy dies, she can no longer eat
from this portion of the קדשים, kodshim, במורם מן הקדשים. bimuram min
hakodshim. So that's just the הלכה halakha that we learn from the
פסוק, pasuk, but for us what's relevant is that קדשים kodshim is
referring to קרבנות. korbanot. Okay, so it's reading these פסוקים pesukim that
these כהנים kohanim are restricted from eating not just like we initially
assumed, קרבנות, korbanot, but they could eat תרומה. terumah. No, since before
they were only eating תרומה דרבנן terumah derabbanan and since there was
a question about their status, according to this answer they can only
continue to eat תרומה דרבנן, terumah derabbanan, they cannot eat תרומה דאורייתא.
terumah de'oraita.
Did you just say before they were eating תרומה דאורייתא? terumah de'oraita?
There are two opinions yesterday. One is that they were eating תרומה
דאורייתא, terumah de'oraita, and nevertheless people would not infer from one to
the other because there had been, the question had been raised, there
was already a stigma. And the other answer was they weren't eating
תרומה דאורייתא, terumah de'oraita, they were only continuing to eat תרומה דרבנן
terumah derabbanan with the additional חידוש chiddush that even though תרומה דרבנן
terumah derabbanan in ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael could lead to possible problems,
they were still eating תרומה דרבנן.
terumah
derabbanan.
That was it, it was the end of yesterday's discussion.
Okay, if she had a son, if she had a son who
was a כהן, kohen, she could eat, right?
Yeah, but this was she was married to a ישראל. Yisrael. But
yes, yes, right. Okay, so, okay, תא שמע. ta shema. So we're
back to this question about going from נשיאת כפיים nesiat kapayim to
יוכסין. yuchsin. Okay, תא שמע. חזקה לכהונה,
Ta shma,
chazaka l'khuna,
a establishment of a presumption, like the word חזקה chazaka means so
many different things in different places, but anyway, here it's like a
presumption of כהונה kehunah is based on נשיאת כפיים בבבל. nesiat kapayim
b'Bavel. In ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael they do דוכנין, duchening, because there's
not really תרומה terumah in בבל, Bavel, and if there is, it's
תרומה דרבנן. terumah derabbanan. דוכנין duchening is a דאורייתא, de'oraita, and to
for a non-כהן kohen to דוכנין duchen would be a דאורייתא de'oraita
problem. So the best evidence that somebody is a כהן kohen for
other purposes, we'll see what other purposes means, that's our question, we're
assuming right now it means יוכסין, yuchsin, is in בבל Bavel that
they do נשיאת כפיים, nesiat kapayim, that they דוכנין. duchen.
ואכילת חלה בסוריא, v'achilat challah b'Surya, סוריא Surya is the area immediately
juxtaposed to ישראל, Yisrael, Syria, Jordan, etc., and those were areas that
were, might have been considered part of קדושת ארץ ישראל kedushat Eretz
Yisrael because they were conquered by דוד, David, King דוד, David, and
that's a whole discussion in the גמרא gemara about כיבוש יחיד. kibush
yachid. Why exactly it's called כיבוש יחיד kibush yachid is not clear,
it's not like he went alone and conquered them. Okay, but there's
a whole discussion about whatever, he did it maybe on his own
without the authority of the סנהדרין Sanhedrin or he did it before
he had finished conquering ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisrael. Also an interesting question
because normally the קדושה kedusha of ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael is based
on בית שני, Bayit Sheni, not בית ראשון. Bayit Rishon. So then
there's some discussion that has to do also with the fact that
the חשמונאים Chashmonaim also conquered those lands. Fascinating questions around סוריא. Surya.
Anyway, סוריא Surya might very well have קדושת ארץ ישראל. kedushat Eretz
Yisrael. So in סוריא Surya we're going to look at the weightier
thing, right? I mean, everywhere there's נשיאת כפיים, nesiat kapayim, but if
there's a weightier evidence, we're going to look at it. So in
סוריא Surya the fact that they eat חלה challah is weightier evidence,
because that has, you know, that's like תרומה terumah and that would
be a חיוב מיתה chiyuv mita if a non-כהן kohen would eat
it.
But that's after the בית המקדש, Beit HaMikdash, the סוריא Surya thing?
Yeah. Can you give today, can you give a כהן חלה kohen
challah today? You didn't really...
Well, no, because we have the whole concern about that everybody is
טמא tamei and so on. Okay. וחילוק מתנות בכרכים, v'chiluk matanot bikrachim,
and giving out the מתנות, matanot, the מתנות matanot here is the
זרוע ולחיים וקיבה, zeroa ulechayayim v'keivah, right, the sections of the of
the arm and whatever, the cheeks of the animal that you slaughter,
giving it to a כהן. kohen. And if you do that in
the cities, why in the cities? Because if you do that in
the towns and the villages, it doesn't prove anything because, you know,
some stranger walks in, says he's a כהן, kohen, people all right,
whatever, they give it to him, they got to give it to
someone.
And there's no איסור, issur, remember, part of the point is that
you would assume that a non-כהן kohen wouldn't do it because it
would be such a violation. It would be an איסור עשה issur
asei to do דוכנין, duchening, it would be a מיתה בידי שמים
mita b'yadei shamayim for תרומה. terumah. Okay, here it's just גזל. gezel.
People don't aren't so concerned about גזל. gezel. So why is it
that it's such a strong evidence? So that's why it has to
be, that's why it has to be בכרכים, bikrachim, because if it's
in the cities, then people say there's like, you know, there's like
a lot of people around. Now you could say well in big
cities everybody is anonymous. But it's a little bit but but but
if you're in a city and you say I'm a כהן, kohen,
everybody says where are you a כהן? kohen? Like there's a lot
of people around and you're afraid that somebody's going to know you
and say you're not a כהן. kohen. Right, if you're in a
village and you're passing through and you say I come from the
other village and I'm a כהן, kohen, they say all right, whatever,
here have some meat, have some of the face. But if you're
in a city, you wouldn't do it. So... That's why although there's
not so much of the איסור issur problem, certain amount of ritual
איסור, issur, even though there's a גזל איסור, gezel issur, but in
the cities, if people, if you're willing to say, "I'm a כהן"
Kohen and "give me some meat" and you're not afraid that somebody's
going to call you on it, that would be also evidence that
you're a כהן. Kohen. Yes.
The vibes change after 20 seconds for me.
Oh shoot. We've had that problem before.
Really? I was wondering why you walked in with your things on.
Alright, and it doesn't look like it ended.
Yeah.
Oh maybe it fits it off air. Let's do this again. Alright.
Sorry.
So they were also doing מתנות כהונה matnot kehuna even after the
חורבן? churban?
What? Yeah, מתנות כהונה, matnot kehuna, yeah I mean that's a whole
discussion, like that more than anything is not based on the בית
המקדש Beis HaMikdash and so on. So there's a whole גמרא Gemara
about that about why we're not נוהג noheig מתנות matnot nowadays.
Isn't it sort of like give a non-Jew a token portion? Is
that it?
No, you're thinking about בכור. bechor. No, the מתנות, matnot, yeah the
מתנות, matnot, there's whatever, there's an opinion in the גמרא Gemara that
you don't have to, but it's not clear why not. Okay, anyway,
let's go. So the גמרא Gemara continues, says this, okay, so, ah,
okay, so that's the ברייתא Braita that we have. So now the
גמרא Gemara continues, קתני מיהת, katani mihat,
we taught nonetheless, נשיאת כפיים. Nesias Kapayim. נשיאת כפיים. Nesias Kapayim. מאי
לאו, mai lav, that
that's evidence of כהונה. kehuna. מאי לאו, mai lav, are we not
talking, hold on one second, okay, מאי לאו, mai
lav, are we not
talking ליוחסין, l'yichsun,
that this is going to be evidence for כהונה kehuna for יוחסין
yichsun purposes? So the גמרא Gemara says, לא לתרומה. lo l'truma.
No, it's only going to be evidence for תרומה, truma, okay, but
not for יוחסין. yichsun. For יוחסין yichsun this will not be enough.
So the גמרא Gemara says, one minute, ובדומיה דאכילת חלה קתני, u-badumya
d'achilas challah katanie, but all of these things are presumably evidence for
the same level of proof that the guy's a כהן. Kohen. So
in בבל Bavel the evidence is he does נשיאת כפיים Nesias Kapayim
and in סוריא Surya the evidence is that he eats חלה. challah.
So we can't be trying to prove he's allowed to eat תרומה
truma because if he's eating חלה challah he's already eating תרומה. truma.
חלה challah is a type of תרומה. truma. So obviously we're proving
something other than his right to eat תרומה. truma. So the גמרא
Gemara says ובדומיה דאכילת חלה קתני, u-badumya d'achilas challah katanie, it says
similar to eating חלה, challah, מה אכילת חלה ליוחסין אף נשיאת כפיים
ליוחסין, ma achilas challah l'yichsun af nesias kapayim l'yichsun, in the same
way eating חלה challah is only relevant for something other than תרומה,
truma, i.e. for יוחסין, yichsun, so דוכן duchaning is relevant for יוחסין,
yichsun, so you see you can go from that ליוחסין. l'yichsun. The
גמרא Gemara says לא, lo, no, not necessarily, אכילת חלה גופה לתרומה,
achilas challah gufah l'truma, no,
חלה challah is also needs to be evidence for תרומה. truma. Why
is תרומה truma different than חלה? challah? If you're already eating חלה
challah you're already eating תרומה. truma. Why do you need this to
be evidence for תרומה? truma? So the גמרא Gemara says no, קסבר
חלה בזמן הזה דרבנן ותרומה דאורייתא. kasavar challah bizman hazeh d'rabbanan v'truma
d'oraisa. No,
cause it's possible to actually say that they're not at the same
level, that חלה challah is only a רבנן rabbanan obligation nowadays and
תרומה truma is דאורייתא. d'oraisa. We'll see why in a minute. And
therefore all of this is how can you prove he's a כהן
Kohen in order to give him תרומה, truma, right, and in order
that he can eat תרומה, truma, and even though he's eating חלה
challah it's not already proven because חלה challah is only רבנן. rabbanan.
But that can still establish him as a כהן Kohen and evidence
that now we can even give him תרומה. truma. Okay, ותרומה דאורייתא.
v'truma d'oraisa. חלה בזמן הזה דרבנן ותרומה דאורייתא ומסקינן מחלה דרבנן לתרומה
דאורייתא. challah bizman hazeh d'rabbanan v'truma d'oraisa u-maskinan m'challah d'rabbanan l'truma d'oraisa.
And the חידוש chiddush is you go from חלה challah which is
רבנן rabbanan to תרומה truma which is דאורייתא. d'oraisa. וכדאפיך להו רב
הונא בריה דרב יהושע לרבנן, u-k'dafich lehu Rav Huna brei d'Rav Yehoshua
l'rabbanan, like רב הונא Rav Huna the son of רב יהושע Rav
Yehoshua reversed it for the רבנן. rabbanan. We're going to see in
a minute that he walked into the בית מדרש Beis Medrash and
the רבנן rabbanan like the rabbis there were saying that חלה challah
is דאורייתא d'oraisa and תרומה truma is דרבנן, d'rabbanan, and he reversed
it. And he said no, חלה challah is דרבנן d'rabbanan and תרומה
truma is דאורייתא. d'oraisa. So we're going to see why in a
minute, but what we're saying now is that all this speaks about
what's evidence that a guy's a כהן Kohen and for what level
of proving he's a כהן Kohen does this show that נשיאת כפיים
Nesias Kapayim can prove he's a כהן Kohen for יוחסין? yichsun? No,
the whole ברייתא Braita is to prove he's a כהן Kohen for
תרומה truma purposes and חלה challah is not already has not already
gotten him there because חלה challah would only be רבנן. rabbanan. That's
the assumption that we are making. Okay, תא שמע, ta shema. let's
try again. חזקה לכהונה, chazaka l'kehunah, he has another ברייתא. Braita. A
presumption of כהונה kehuna can be based on the following things. נשיאת
כפיים וחילוק גרנות בארץ ישראל. Nesias Kapayim v'chiluk granos b'Eretz Yisroel.
So in ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisroel, either דוכן duchaning or, and here's
the word חילוק גרנות, chiluk granos, which is a point I made
before, not just eating תרומה, truma, but distributing of תרומה truma in
the in the warehouses, in the granaries, in the grain houses,
that's in ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisroel. ובסוריא ובכל מקום ששלוחי ראש חודש
מגיעין, u-v'Surya u-v'chol makom she-shluchei Rosh Chodesh magiin, all the places that
the messengers of בית דין Beis Din were sent out from ארץ
ישראל Eretz Yisroel and they could get there you know and they
were sort of they get there to deliver the news about when
ראש חודש Rosh Chodesh was within like 15 days travel from ארץ
ישראל. Eretz Yisroel. So those places, which is presumably not קדושת ארץ
ישראל kedushas Eretz Yisroel for תרומות ומעשרות, trumos u-maasros, so distributing תרומה
truma is not such an evidence. So what is it going to
be? נשיאת כפיים ראיה, Nesias Kapayim raiya,
only דוכן duchaning because that is still a דאורייתא d'oraisa there, אבל
לא חילוק גרנות, aval lo chiluk granos, but not distributing of תרומה
truma because it's not דאורייתא. d'oraisa. So you will notice first of
all two things. Number one is that סוריא Surya switched sides in
this ברייתא. Braita. In the previous ברייתא braita. *Baraisa* סוריא *Surya* giving
out תרומה terumah *Truma* was evidence, here it is not. So רש״י
*Rashi* tells us that presumably the debate of the ברייתות braitas *Baraisas*
is what is the halachic status of סוריא *Surya*? Does סוריא *Surya*
have קדושת ארץ ישראל kedushas Eretz Yisrael, *kedushas Eretz Yisroel* or not?
In the first ברייתא braita *Baraisa* is that it did, so a
כהן kohein *kohein* eating תרומה terumah. *Truma* in סוריא *Surya* was good
evidence or eating חלה challah. *challah* and תרומה terumah *Truma*, and in
this ברייתא beraisa *Baraisa*, סוריא *Surya* is assumed to not have קדושת
ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael *kedushas Eretz Yisroel*. Fine. So therefore it's back
to דוכנינג duchening, *duchaning*. Why is it dependent on where the שלוחי
בית דין Beis Din *shluchei beis din* go? What does that have
to do with anything? So רש״י *Rashi* says, well if the שלוחי
בית דין *shluchei beis din* go there that means that there is
some of the apparatus of the court in those areas, there are
other courts that are sort of satellite courts in those areas, and
here becomes the point that it's not just this person in terms
of his individual observance would never do this thing if he weren't
a כהן kohein, *kohein*. It's also as I mentioned yesterday, how much
is the ציבור *tzibur*'s sort of silent acceptance of it part of
what creates the assumption that he's a כהן kohein *kohein*? So if
it's a place where everybody is ignorant, right, and there's nobody that
sort of or even if people know the הלכה halacha *halacha*, nobody
cares and nobody is on top of things, so then the fact
that he's doing it doesn't prove too much. But if it's a
place where there's a satellite court systems and there are learned people
and people that are concerned about the observance level of the community
and he's still going ahead and doing this behavior then it is
more evident. Okay, so that's important in terms of conceptualizing what's creating
this presumption. It's A, he has to be doing something that's weighty,
that there would be real serious religious consequence to like halachic consequence
to if he were not a כהן kohen *kohein*, and B, that
the community is implicitly accepting it and therefore it has to be
a community that would care. Okay, and that's why the idea of...
A and B?
A and B. It's he's doing it and the community is accepting
it. And therefore it's only in the case where it's a community
that would care. What's the religious significance here for נשיאת כפיים nesias
kapayim, *nesias kapayim*?
It's an איסור עשה asei *issur asei* for a non-כהן kohen. *kohein*
to do it. Interesting. Just there would be a halachic problem. Okay,
so I mean an halachic problem usually at the דאורייתא d'oraisa. *de'oraisa*
level, which is why we're trying to identify things that are דאורייתא
d'oraisa. *de'oraisa*. Okay, it's a weighty type of a halachic violation, which
is why חילוק גרנות *chiluk granot* in סוריא *Surya* would not be
an issue because that would only be דרבנן derabbanan *derabbanan*, but נשיאת
כפיים nesiyas kapayim *nesias kapayim* would. Right, so that's the basic thing
that's guiding this. A, to identify something that is a weighty violation
and B, to do it in a context in which the ציבור
*tzibur* is countenancing it and the ציבור *tzibur* would care if he
should not be doing it.
רבן שמעון בן גמליאל אומר אף על אלכסנדריא של מצרים *Rabban Shimon
ben Gamliel omer af al Alexandri'ah shel Mitzrayim*. Okay, even Alexandria of
Egypt, which is fascinating because obviously it was a there was a
lot of Jews
there. It's cosmopolitan and it was very assimilated, you know, so at
least from what I understand. So it's quite fascinating that that's considered
but again, it might be assimilated, but you know, it could be
some of the things that they remained מקפיד *makpid* on were כהונה
kehuna *kehuna* issues and status issues and טומאה וטהרה *tum'ah v'taharah* issues,
right? So assimilation could have been in other areas but maybe דווקא
davka *davka* this was something people were מקפיד *makpid* on. So therefore
behavior that was tolerated there would be significant. Okay, one minute. בראשונה
*Barishona* initially מפני שבית דין קבועים שם *mipnei shebeis din kvuim sham*.
So the key word here though that qualifies that is initially. Maybe
originally we had an outpost in Alexandria. So therefore if we had
an outpost in Alexandria, behavior done there would have been significant that
we that we were had silent acquiescence to. But the implicit point
might be but nowadays they've gone you know so off the דרך
*derech* and we don't have an outpost there anymore and you can't
go by anything that happens in Alexandria. Yes.
Time's thought suggested the reason it was initially was by the time
of רבי Rabbi שמעון בן גמליאל *Rabbi Shimon ben Gamliel*, the Alexandrian
community had been destroyed by the Romans. Aha.
Persecution in...
Oh, so it's not that it's about being less assimilated and more
assimilated. About being there or not being there. Yeah. I don't know,
doesn't sound that way. It sounds like the difference was how much
was there a presence of a בית דין
*beis din* there, but yeah. The other question is, there was a
type of a temple in Alexandria. Yeah.
בית חוניו *Beis Chonyo*.
Yeah. But I don't know did they actually have priests doing...
Yeah, that's a good question. Yeah, I don't know. I mean it's
fascinating that Alexandria was like a place we could actually
go by.
This whole discussion assumes the possibility that we could recognize someone as
a כהן kohen? enough to allow them to eat תרומה terumah, but
not enough to do עבודה avodah in the בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash.
Right, or not enough for marriage purposes, correct. Right, it's very funny,
like how do you, it's very hard to
sustain, it's very hard to sustain, like you would imagine a society
in which personal status is partially recognized. You know, but it does
by the way happen like
a lot, having a green card but you can't...
Well, you know, but it happens all the time I got to
tell you, like if it's on a college campus, and it happens
in shuls, but it happens on a college campus. Somebody walks into
the מנין minyan and says, oh I'm Jewish, and you know and
they basically, do you give them an עליה? aliyah? Do you count
them to מנין? minyan? Whatever. You know, and the question is like
what? Do you start, do you have to say wizard of oz?
Well, first let's have a whole conversation. Why do you, why do
you think you're Jewish? Da da da. And how much does he
have to investigate? Or, you know, at certain things, for things like
that which are basically like דרבנן derabbanan things, there's a גמרא gemara
that basically says if somebody says they're Jewish, they're נאמן, ne'eman, right?
So how much do you sort of, you know, not, I mean,
I'm not saying somebody comes and says to the rabbi, by the
way you should know the reason he says he's Jewish is because
his father was Jewish but his mother was Catholic and whatever. So
then obviously it's different. But without knowing anything else, right, do you
give somebody a presumption if they say they're Jewish, they're Jewish? But
then if the guy starts now saying I want you to marry
me, right, you know, then a different type of an issue, then
requires a different level of בירור. beirur. So this actually becomes a
very like relevant thing that happens on a regular basis, you know.
And then I should mention the fascinating question is, because this is
so much, I got to tell you, this גמרא gemara we're learning
is so irrelevant, but this is so relevant to this question. I'm
the rabbi of that מנין, minyan, so I know, look, what am
I going to do? I'm going to give the guy the third
degree? He walked in, he says it's his יארצייט, yahrzeit, he says
he wants to דאוון daven for the עמוד, amud, right? I'm going
to say, well, first I have to see your papers, I got
to know that you're Jewish, right? Okay, but one minute! But you
know, but the whole issue about מעלין ma'alin is then of course
this guy's Jewish! He's been going to the, he's been going to
the Orthodox מנין minyan on campus for the last four years, they've
been giving him עליות, aliyos, they've been doing this, they've been doing
that, so then once you start sort of at one level, that
creates presumptions that go beyond that, right? And that's the whole issue,
מעלין מתרומה ליוחסין, ma'alin mi'trumah l'yuchsin, right?
So actually this stuff is highly relevant, yes.
I walked into the big synagogue in Vancouver, British Columbia a few
years ago and said, I'm saying קדיש Kaddish for my father's יארצייט.
yahrzeit. And they said, no, you're not just doing that, you're דאוונינג
davening from the עמוד. amud. They'd never seen me before. Right, right.
I was
flabbergasted and I דאוונד davened three services.
Yeah, but there's also questions sometimes, it's also about how somebody looks,
you know, as well, you know, so but yes.
But at the end of the day, what do we do? I
mean, so if a כהן kohen. walks in, like you know, להלכה
ולמעשה, l'halacha u'l'ma'aseh, so someone walks into the מנין, minyan, says they're
כהן, kohen?
we believe them.
Okay, in the זמן הזה. zman hazeh.
Yeah, we're not so afraid now for יוחסין yuchsin and for whatever.
Okay, let's move on. Alright, so,
okay, קתני מיהת, katani mihat, then we taught nonetheless, נשיאת כפים, nesiat
kapayim, that again נשיאת כפים nesiat kapayim is evidence. Okay, for something.
So what's it evidence for? מאי לאו ליוחסין, mai lav l'yuchsin, again,
are we not talking about יוחסין? yuchsin? לא, לחלה, lo, l'challah, no,
we mean is it good enough evidence that we can give him
and he can eat חלה. challah So the גמרא gemara says one
minute, but the other evidence it said was the eating of תרומה.
terumah הא דומיא דחילוק גרנות קתני, ha dumya d'chiluk granot katani,
but one of the other things that could serve as evidence that
he's a כהן kohen. is that we give him תרומה terumah. in
the, you know, in the granaries. So מה חילוק גרנות ליוחסין, mah
chiluk granot l'yuchsin,
so the same way that's not about חלה challah because he's already,
we're already giving him תרומה, terumah so it must be about a
different, a higher level, it must be that that's evidence even for
marriage purposes.
So אף נשיאת כפים ליוחסין, af nesiat kapayim l'yuchsin, so the same
will be, is about דוכנינג, that we're talking about what will serve
as evidence for marriage purposes, so right, because the תרומה terumah. issue's
already been solved and the חלה challah issue's been solved. גמרא gemara
says no. לא, חילוק גרנות גופא לחלה, lo, chiluk granot gufah l'challah,
no,
we're doing the reverse of what we did in the previous ברייתא.
braita The previous ברייתא braita said he was eating חלה challah. and
we said, oh, that's only to prove that he can eat תרומה.
terumah. תרומה terumah is at a higher level than חלה. challah, Here
we're flipping it. It says that he's eating תרומה. terumah What's that
evidence for? That's evidence to let him eat חלה, challah because חלה
challah is at a higher level than תרומה. terumah Okay. לא, דקסבר
תרומה בזמן הזה דרבנן וחלה דאורייתא, lo, d'kasvar terumah bazman hazeh derabbanan
v'challah d'oraisa, that currently תרומה terumah is the thing that's דרבנן derabbanan.
and חלה challah is דאורייתא. d'oraisa? ומסקינן מתרומה דרבנן לחלה דאורייתא, u'maskinan
mi'trumah derabbanan l'challah d'oraisa, and the חידוש chiddush is you go from
תרומה trumah. which is rabbinic to חלה challah which is דאורייתא. d'oraisa
ו-, u-,
and now we're going to have the final story where we have
the ideas that חלה challah and תרומה trumah are the opposite of
one another, but both possibilities. וכדאשכחינהו רב הונא בריה דרב יהושע לרבנן,
u'ch'dashkechin'hu Rav Huna brei d'Rav Yehoshua l'rabbanan, like רב הונא בריה דרב
יהושע Rav Huna brei d'Rav Yehoshua found the rabbis, דאמר רב הונא
בריה דרב יהושע, d'amar Rav Huna brei d'Rav Yehoshua, because רב הונא
בריה דרב יהושע Rav Huna brei d'Rav Yehoshua said, אשכחתינהו לרבנן בבי
רב, ashkachtinehu l'rabbanan be'vei Rav,
I found the rabbis in the house of רב, Rav, in the
ישיבה yeshiva of רב, Rav, דיתבי וקאמרי, d'yasvi v'ka'amri, they were sitting
and they were saying, אפילו למאן דאמר תרומה בזמן הזה דרבנן, afilu
l'man d'amar terumah bazman hazeh derabbanan,
even if you say, you see now I did like the
whole בית מדרש beis medrash ניגון, niggun, אפילו למאן דאמר, afilu l'man
d'amar, even if you say that nowadays, because that's how
they were saying it, even if you say that nowadays תרומה trumah.
is rabbinic. ז' שכיבשו וז' שחילקו, Zayin She-kivshu V'zayin She-chilku,
the first 14 years when they entered into ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael.
in the time of Yehoshua, that they were conquering and dividing the
land. Okay? נתחייבו בחלה ולא נתחייבו בתרומה. Nischayvu B'challa V'lo Nischayvu B'trumah.
They were חייב chayav in חלה challah and not in תרומה. trumah
Okay? So, how do they, how do we know that? And also,
what does that prove? So we know it because by חלה challah.
it says, בבואכם אל הארץ, B'voachem El Ha'aretz, as soon as you
enter into the land. So as from the very moment they entered,
they were חייב chayav in חלה. challah Whereas by other cases of
תרומות ומעשרות, trumos u'ma'asros, right, it doesn't, it's, I mean, sometimes it
says כי תבוא אל הארץ, ki tavo el ha'aretz, but somehow בבואכם
b'voachem is understood as as soon as you enter. Whereas other cases
it says sort of like כי תבואו אל הארץ וישבתם בה וירשתם
אותה וישבתם בה. ki tavo'u el ha'aretz v'yashavtem bah v'yirashtem osah v'yashavtem
bah. So there's a, so by other cases the sense is that
you have to actually settle it and conquer it before you're obligated.
Whereas by חלה challah. the דרשה drasha is that as soon as
they entered in they're חייב. chayav. So what does that show you?
So presumably what he's saying is why would תרומה trumah nowadays not
be דאורייתא? d'oraisa. It wouldn't be דאורייתא d'oraisa because we would say
the קדושה kedusha would no longer be exist. Why would the קדושה
kedusha no longer exist? Right? Because why would קדושה ראשונה לא קידשה
לעתיד לבוא, קדושה שנייה לא קידשה לעתיד לבוא? Kedusha Rishona Lo Kidsha
L'asid Lavo, Kedusha Shniya Lo Kidsha L'asid Lavo?
Because once it's destroyed, once it's, once the exile, maybe the קדושה
kedusha goes away. Okay. Now what is the exile the opposite of?
What is the exile is opposite of being settled in the land,
being having dominion over the land. So if you need to have
dominion over the land in order to instill the קדושה, kedusha, you
could say that when you are exiled, the קדושה kedusha goes away.
But that's תרומה. trumah But if you didn't need dominion, you just
need presence, right, you just entered the land and it had the
קדושה kedusha and you'd be חייב chayav in חלה. challah. So then
even now that there's exile and there's no dominion and it's the
Romans are in charge and all of that, our very presence might
be enough to be חייב chayav in חלה. challah It's a very
beautiful לימוד. limmud. So חלה challah because you're חייב chayav when they
walk in before they have dominion, that חיוב chiyuv would remain even
nowadays even if it would not have קדושה kedusha for תרומה trumah
purposes in ארץ ישראל.
Eretz Yisrael תרומה truma and
קדושה kedusha for קדושה kedusha purposes has to do with dominion over
the land.
But this חיוב chiyuv of חלה challah sort of that is independent
even of the presence of the human being there.
Well, you can't be חייב chayav if you're not actually there.
Well, but
not, it's not independent of the presence, it's independent of, they had
to have entered the land, but it's independent of them having dominion
over the land, over them settling the land, conquering the land, yeah.
When did the מן mahn stop?
The מן mahn stopped right ערב פסח. erev pesach. Doesn't it say
ממחרת הפסח? Mimacharas HaPesach? It says
it started by ערב פסח erev pesach it stopped. Yes.
It was days after we entered.
Yes, the first, as soon as after we entered.
After we entered, yeah, it's like yeah, one or two...
Okay
so that let's hear let's hear
the other side of the argument. So I like that, that's rabbi...
Yes it's an interesting sequence like if it stopped before ערב פסח
erev pesach then they had מצה matzah right. And so the first
bread they would eat would have to bring
חלה challah according to this, that's a nice point. Okay, very nice
point. Okay, so that's one version of it. Now let's, so that
has חלה דאורייתא. challah d'oraisa. So according to that version, the ברייתא
braita. that says you can have evidence of תרומה truma and נשיאת
כפיים, nesiyas kapayim we don't have to say תרומה נשיאת כפיים trumah
nesias kapayim means for יחוס yichus because it could mean for חלה
challah because חלה challah is דאורייתא. d'oraisa Okay,
that's one version. ואמינא להו אנא, V'amina Lehu Ana, and I said
back to them, אדרבה, adaraba, no, the opposite is the case. אפילו
למאן דאמר תרומה בזמן הזה דאורייתא, Afilu L'man D'amar Terumah Bazman Hazeh
D'oraisa, even if תרומה truma is דאורייתא d'oraisa. because the קדושה kedusha
of ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael remains nowadays, חלה דרבנן, challah derabbanan, חלה
challah remains דרבנן. d'rabonon.
Why? דתניא, D'tanya, בבואכם, b'voachem, when you enter in. So before we
said that means as soon as you enter, but here we're going
to say another point. אל הארץ, El ha'aretz, אי בבואכם יכול משנכנסו
לה שנים ושלושה מרגלים, i b'voachem yachol mishenichnasu lah shnayim v'shlosha meraglim,
maybe even if two or three spies were sent in, maybe even
one or two people go in. תלמוד לומר בבואכם, Talmud lomar b'voachem,
no, the כם chem means בביאת כולכם, b'vias kulchem, only when all
of you enter in.
אמרתי ולא בביאת מקצתכם, Amarti v'lo b'vias miktzaschem, not only when part
of you. Now, fine. Okay, so maybe that's needed initially to instill
the קדושה. kedusha. But he says but maybe it's also needed for
the קדושה kedusha the second time around as well. Do we go
by the first קדושה kedusha or the second קדושה? kedusha? וכי אסיקנו
עזרא V'chi askinu Ezra when Ezra brought them in, we're back to
Ezra like we were just a minute ago talking about the re-entering
into the land and the כהנים kohanim and so on. So when
Ezra brought them in, לאו כולהו סליק, lav kulu salli, not all
of them did not come up, only a minority of the people
returned from the exile, right, in the time of Ezra, and therefore
it was not resanctified for חלה challah purposes. So here's a fascinating
question. You can go by, you can go to opposite extremes. One
extreme is that חלה challah, does not require קדושת ארץ ישראל, Eretz
Yisrael which is fascinating, right, it's based on the grain and so
on. But on the other hand, it's not just the grain, it's
only when the grain is turned into חלה, challa, right, so it
is a little different, so you could say... Maybe it's less linked
to the קדושה kedusha because it doesn't, it's not the grain itself
is חייב chayav in חלה, challa it's only when you actually turn
it into dough. So maybe it's less linked from the immediate experience
of having grown from the ground. So that's the idea that it's
not so linked to the קדושה kedusha of ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael
and therefore חלה challa could be דאורייתא and תרומה truma דרבנן. rabbinic
And then you have the reverse. It might require a higher level
of קדושה, kedusha, it might require קדושה kedusha that was instilled not
just by the re-entry, not just by Ezra
and whoever came in at the time, but it had to be
a קדושה kedusha of all of כלל ישראל, Klal Yisrael, which is
like a fascinating idea. Why of all things would חלה challa require
a higher level of קדושה? kedusha? But because you could go one,
reverse it, and say there are different levels one way or the
other, a ברייתא braita. that says you go from חלה challa and
נשיאת כפיים nesiyas kapayim for כהונה kehuna, purposes might not mean יוחסין,
yuchsin, might just mean חלה challa. which is דרבנן and נשיאת כפיים
nesiyas kapayim which is an עשה aseh to תרומה truma which is
a דאורייתא. Or a ברייתא Braisa. that says נשיאת כפיים nesiyas kapayim
and תרומה truma. might not mean נשיאת כפיים nesiyas kapayim. and תרומה
truma, for יוחסין, yuchsin, it might mean נשיאת כפיים nesiyas kapayim and
תרומה truma for חלה. challa? So because you could reverse it, the
ברייתות don't have to mean נשיאת כפיים.
nesiyas kapayim, Just a second, what I don't understand. One is a
ביאה bi'ah and that's also talking about the initial ביאה, bi'ah, so
what does Ezra have to do with this? No, they had the
ביאה bi'ah in the סיפא. sayfa.
כהנים Cohanim came then, but the assumption is is that the קדושה
kedusha of the first time is קדושה ראשונה קידשה לשעתה ולא קידשה
לעתיד לבוא. kedusha rishona kidsha l'shaata v'lo kidsha l'asid lavo. It required
a second קדושה kedusha in the time of Ezra, and that second
קדושה kedusha was patterned after the first קדושה. kedusha. But that's the
assumption, yeah.
But the other assumption is that with the other one then, the
first way, is that okay, so then that since there there were
נתנה חויבו בחלה בזמן שכבשו netana chayvu bechalla be-zman she-kibshu and it's
a matter of the grain, so let's say I import or whatever,
I'm a grain importer, I import ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael grain, I'm
in בבל, Bavel, do I have to take חלה?
challa. Right, so that's the question. Is it basically saying that the
חיוב גברא chiyuv gavra if you happen to be in ארץ ישראל
Eretz Yisrael. or is there a different level of קדושה? kedusha? There's
just it grew from ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael. even though it didn't
have the קדושה kedusha of ארץ ישראל. Yisrael Yes, so that's those
are interesting questions. I mean this גמרא, gemara, this is a really
fun, if you would, or interesting גמרא gemara because it raises the
level, the question of this idea of like different levels of קדושה
kedusha and different senses of a חיוב chiyuv without קדושה kedusha but
still based on grain of
ארץ ישראל.
Yisrael Yeah, there's inter-
no, no, no, it's not a total גברא gavra thing. But anyway,
but no, there is interesting discussions about this. Okay. תא שמע. ta
shema, Come and let's come and do. חזקה, Chazaka, so we still
don't know. Do you go from נשיאת כפיים nesiyas kapayim to יוחסין?
yuchsin? We've been trying and trying and we haven't proven it. Okay.
תא שמע Ta shma. חזקה לכהונה, chazakah l'kehuna, the presumption of כהונה,
kehuna? נשיאת כפיים, nesiyas kapayim. doing duchening, וחילוק גרנות, v'chiluk gornot, and
the distribution of תרומה. truma, So again, either or. Again we would
presume that would mean therefore for יוחסין yuchsin because he's already eating
תרומה, truma. but the גמרא gemara can always say it means for
חלה. Challah Okay, but now we have a third thing. ועדות. V'eidus.
And testimony. So what does that mean? What do you have to
presume he's a כהן kohen, for testimony purposes? So ועדות חזקה
היא? v'eidus, chazaka hi? Is עדות eidus a חזקה? chazaka? Okay, meaning
and so it seems maybe it means that עדים edim came and
said that he was a כהן. kohen. So then what do you
mean that's a חזקה chazaka that he's a כהן? kohen עדים Edim
are saying that he's a כהן. kohen, אלא לאו הכי קאמר. Ela
lav hachi kamar. No, no, no, this is what it must mean.
נשיאת כפיים כעדות. Nesiyas kapayim k'eidus. If he's doing all these other
things, duchening and eating תרומה truma or being distributing תרומה, truma, excuse
me I should say, are as strong as direct testimony that he
is. The only reason to throw in testimony is to make the
point that they're all at an equal level. You want to know
how he's a כהן? Cohen. Here's how you can know he's a
כהן. Cohen. You can have testimony that he's a כהן, Cohen. you
could see him doing נשיאת כפיים Nesiat Kapayim? or you could see
him giving תרומה. trumah. So if I say that, even though the
first thing was obvious, what it sent it sent a message that
all these things are just as good as testimony, that all these
things totally prove he's a כהן. Cohen? Okay, so that's a pretty
good read of that ברייתא. braisa, Okay, so נשיאת כפיים כעדות לכהונה,
nesiyas kapayim k'eidus l'khuna, נשיאת כפ-
nesiyas kap- oh that could be.
Okay, that's
true.
נשיאת כפיים כעדות, Nesiyas kapayim k'eidus, it's just as good as direct
testimony. מה עדות ליוחסין, Ma eidus l'yuchsin, the same way testimony would
work for יוחסין, yuchsin, אף נשיאת כפיים ליוחסין. af nesiyas kapayim l'yuchsin.
Even duchening. So that seems to be a nice read of that
ברייתא. braisa But the גמרא gemara rejects it because it's not explicit.
לא, Lo, not necessarily.
עדות הבאה מכח חזקה כחזקה. Eidus haba'ah mi-koach chazaka k'chazaka. A testimony
that is based on a presumption is as good as the presumption
itself if we directly witness the presumption. So witness hearing one degree
removed, testimony about a presumption, is like is like directly seeing the
things that lead to the presumption. What is this testimony about a
presumption? So now we're going to have, you could just say somebody
comes and testifies, I saw the כהן Cohen. get תרומה trumah in
the, was distributed תרומה, Terumah I saw this guy do נשיאת כפיים.
Nesiat Kapayim. So we as it were the בית דין didn't see
it, but somebody is reporting that they saw it.
No, presumption means we see certain facts and that allows us to
draw certain inferences. Okay, so let's see what the גמרא gemara says
that that means. It's a little bit more nuanced than just being
second, being reported to rather than directly witnessed. כי ההוא, Ki hahu,
like the following case, and now this is going to be the
case that everybody was asking me yesterday about, which is how we
would mostly assume somebody's a כהן, Cohen which is what עליה aliya
did he get? כי ההוא דאתא לקמיה דרבי אמי. Ki hahu d'ata
lekamei d'Rabbi Ami. A person came before רבי אמי. Rabbi Ami. כי
הא דאתא לקמיה דרבי אמי Kehai de'ata lekamei de'Rabbi Ami a person
came to Rabbi Ami. אמר ליה Amar le מוחזקני בזה שהוא כהן
Muchzani b'ze shehu Cohen I have a presumption I have a basis
to assume that this guy we're talking about is a כהן. Cohen
אמר ליה Amar le מה ראית Ma re'ita what did you see
that makes you assume this? אמר ליה Amar le he said to
him שקרא ראשון בבית הכנסת Shekara rishon b'veit hakeneset because he read
first in the shul בחזקת שהוא כהן. b'chezkat shehu Cohen. I'm sorry,
בבית הכנסת. b'veit hakeneset. He was given the first עליה aliya in
the shul. So that's to me evidence that he's a כהן. Cohen
So then he said back to him, that's what he said back
to him. אמר ליה Amar le he said back to him בחזקת
שהוא כהן b'chezkat shehu Cohen או בחזקת שהוא גדול? o b'chezkat shehu
gadol? So how do you know why he was given the first
עליה? aliya? The הלכה is, at least in principle, although this is
not our practice, that if you have a תלמיד חכם talmid chacham
or a, you give them the first עליה aliya before a כהן.
Cohen So how do you know just because he got the first
עליה, aliya, maybe he was a big תלמיד חכם, talmid chacham, maybe
he was a גדול? gadol? Okay, maybe he was an important person,
maybe that's why. So how do you know that that proves he's
a כהן? Cohen. And he said he always was given the first
עליה. aliya. Sure he's always given the first עליה aliya because he's
a תלמיד חכם, talmid chacham, because he's a גדול. gadol.
I guess they don't, they never
called him up by כהן. Cohen Well, that's a good point, that's
a good question. Maybe they didn't have the, they didn't say הכהן.
ha'Cohen. Okay, anyway. So how do you know in what capacity he
was called up?
שקרא אחריו לוי. Shekara achrav Levi. No, because he, not only did
they give him the first עליה, aliya, they gave a לוי Levi
after him. Now what does that prove? Because this raises an interesting
discussion in רש"י Rashi and תוספות. Tosafot. One minute, so if you
do give a big תלמיד חכם talmid chacham the first עליה, aliya,
you're not allowed to call a לוי Levi afterwards? Right? Maybe they
gave him the first and they gave לוי Levi after. So רש"י
Rashi has one answer which is, that's right, you're not allowed to.
If you give him the first one, so as not to confuse
things, you דווקא davka, don't give a לוי Levi after him to
make it clear that this is not because he's a כהן Cohen,
and we're not doing, we're not doing that whole כהן Cohen לוי
Levi thing today. We're doing who's a more important person thing today.
No, joke, right. So you דווקא, davka right, so you דווקא would
not give a לוי. Levi. That was one answer. The second answer
of רש"י Rashi is more nuanced. It says no, if there was,
if there was no כהן Cohen in the בית הכנסת, beit hakeneset,
you could give a לוי Levi next. But if there were כהן
Cohen. in the shul and instead you gave the תלמיד חכם, talmid
chacham, you can't give a לוי Levi next. Presumably because that's like
more deeply offensive to the כהן. Cohen It's like then it, then
it sort of keeps the basic structure where we're doing כהן לוי
ישראל Kohen Levi Yisrael but instead of you, the כהן, Cohen. we're
giving it to someone else. Okay, so therefore if there is a
כהן Cohen. in the בית הכנסת, beit hakeneset, then you would not
do לוי, Levi you would work with a different paradigm. Right, anyway.
So therefore according to that, the idea was was that there was
a כהן Cohen. in the בית הכנסת beit hakeneset and nevertheless they
gave him first and a לוי Levi, next. That proves that he
is a כהן. Cohen. Okay, yes.
The גמרא Gemara knows how to say תלמיד חכם. talmid chacham. You
said important person interchangeably. Is it only a תלמיד חכם talmid chacham
or could it be the wealthy person who helps the shul?
Yeah, so it could be the second. I mean more, more I
have to double check the discussion in גיטין. Gittin. More normally the
discussion is about giving like a תלמיד חכם talmid chacham first. But
you're right, the גמרא Gemara does say גדול gadol which is a
broader, which is
broader. I'm trying to remember what תוספות's Tosafot way
is.
The term they use
is,
oh no, so תוספות Tosafot is even more complicated. It says no,
here's what happened. They gave this guy the first עליה. aliya. They
gave a לוי Levi who was a very nonsubstantial person the second
עליה, aliya, nonsubstantial status, and then they gave a ישראל Yisrael who
was of greater status the third עליה. aliya. Wow. So that was
proof that they were doing כהן Cohen לוי Levi ישראל Yisrael because
if they were doing it based on status, the ישראל would have
had before the לוי. Levi Anyway. All right, one way or another,
the fact that the לוי Levi. came after is proof that he
was a כהן. Cohen All right, so that was the proof that
he got an
עליה. aliya. והעליהו רבי אמי לכהונה על פיו Ve'aleihu Rabbi Ami likhuna
al piv and Rabbi Ami therefore was able to assume that he
was a כהן. Cohen. Now there's a couple of questions here. We've
been tearing our hair out to figure out can you go from
נשיאת כפים nesiat kapayim which is an עשה to יוחסין yuchsin and
here we're going just from the fact that a guy got an
עליה aliya and establishing that he's a כהן. Kohen But it doesn't
tell you for what purpose he's established he's a כהן. Kohen. Maybe
it means for, you know, I don't know, for תרומה. Terumah? Maybe
it means for to give him the, to give him the עליה
aliya in this new shul. I mean it's not exactly clear for
what purposes, right? It's certainly we would assume based on all the
discussion earlier that we're not talking about יוחסין. yuchsin. That's number one.
Number two though is so what does this show? What does this
mean עדות אחזקה? edut achazaka? So one way to read it is
just look, we didn't see it directly, he reported it. But תוספות
Tosafot says no, it's a little bit more nuanced here. עדות אחזקה
edut achazaka means as opposed to like seeing him eat תרומה Terumah,
and seeing him do נשיאת כפים, nesiat kapayim, there we directly saw
him doing activity that only a כהן Kohen. would do. Here the
only way we knew he was a כהן Kohen, was not just
that he got the first עליה, aliya, it was based on something
that happened afterwards which was based on who got the second עליה.
aliya. So that's a type of an עדות אחזקה edut achazaka meaning
it's like a, you know, it's like not even direct עדות edut
of what he did, it's עדות edut based on the presumption based
on what we saw afterwards happen in terms of the second עליה.
aliya. All right, anyway we're back to our idea that we don't
know that you can go although there seems to be a lot
of evidence you can go from נשיאת כפים nesiat kapayim to יוחסין.
yuchsin. We've been resisting it and we've had other explanations. But now
what we had introduced also is seeing a guy get the first
עליה aliya in shul and using that as a basis at least
for some level of presuming he's a כהן. Kohen. And now we're
going to have another similar story. Let's take a look. ההוא דאתא
לקמיה דרבי יהושע בן לוי. Hahu de'ata lekamei de'Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi.
A person came to רבי יהושע בן לוי. Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi.
אמר ליה, Amar lei, said to him, מוחזקני בזה שהוא לוי. muchzakni
b'zeh she'hu Levi. I know this guy's a לוי. Levi אמר ליה,
Amar lei, מה ראית? mah ra'ita? What did you see? אמר ליה,
Amar lei, שקרא שני בבית הכנסת. she'kara sheni be'veit haknesset. He got
the second עלייה aliyah in
the
בית הכנסת. Beit Knesset. בחזקת שהוא לוי או בחזקת שהוא גדול? be'chezkat
she'hu Levi o be'chezkat she'hu gadol? How do you know? Was it
because it was presumed that he was a לוי Levi. or presumed
that he was maybe a חשוב chashuve person? So the גמרא Gemara
says, no, שקרא לפניו כהן. she'kara lefanav Kohen. No, because we were
keeping the structure, a כהן Kohen. got the first עלייה. aliyah. So
we weren't doing the structure of
who has more status and so on. We're doing the כהן Kohen?
לוי Levi ישראל structure and he got the second עלייה. aliyah. דליי
רבי יהושע בן לוי ללוי על פיו. de'lei Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi
l'Levi al piv. So רבי יהושע בן לוי, Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi,
interestingly, was willing to consider him a לוי. Levi. What does that
mean? It means for giving him מעשר. ma'aser. Okay. Okay, now. So
two interesting stories about going from getting an עלייה aliyah in שול
shul for תרומה Terumah? and מעשר, Ma'aser, but still יוחסין yuchsin remains
the gold standard.
ההוא דאתא לקמיה דריש לקיש. Hahu de'ata lekamei de'Reish Lakish. A certain
person came to ריש לקיש. Reish Lakish. אמר ליה, Amar lei, מוחזקני
בזה שהוא כהן. muchzakni b'zeh she'hu Kohen. I know that this guy's
a כהן. Kohen. אמר ליה, Amar lei, מה ראית? mah ra'ita? On
basis of what? אמר ליה, Amar lei, שקרא ראשון בבית הכנסת. she'kara
rishon be'veit haknesset. He got the first עלייה aliyah in the שול.
shul. And again, maybe there was something, they had the whole other
discussion that a לוי Levi got after him. But now we're going
to have another perspective. אמר ליה, Amar lei, said to him, ראית
שחלק על הגרנות? ra'ita she'chilek al hagranot? One minute, but did you
ever see him directly get distributed
תרומה? Terumah, For he was not impressed that the guy got an
עלייה aliyah in שול. shul. Meaning, even if he got an עלייה
aliyah and the לוי Levi got afterwards, right, until now we've said
that one of the things that's the proof is that the person
is doing something that would be a serious
violation, right? דוכנין. duchanin. If a לא כהן lo Kohen were to
דוכנין, duchan, it would be a serious violation. Eating תרומה, Terumah? right?
So it's not just that he did some behavior. He did a
behavior that was a serious violation if he weren't a כהן. Kohen.
So since when can we make any presumptions that he got the
first עלייה? aliyah? Somebody walks into שול, shul, says he's a כהן,
Kohen says, "Yeah, I'd like to get the first עלייה, aliyah, I'm
a כהן." Kohen, Okay, so you know, he's that's not a serious
violation. So what type of presumption can you make? So ריש לקיש
Reish Lakish pushed back, "I'm not impressed that he got the first
עלייה. aliyah. Did you see him ever get distributed תרומה? Terumah That's
the type of thing I want to be looking at." One minute.
So that's what ריש לקיש Reish Lakish said back to him. אמר
ליה רבי אלעזר, Amar le'Rabbi Elazar, so רבי אלעזר Rabbi Elazar was
there and he said, "ואם אין שם גורן בטלה כהונה?" v'im ein
sham goren batla kehuna? He says, "And I don't get it. If
there's no threshing floor, if there's no גורן goren in that town,
so therefore we can have no presumptions of כהונה?" kehuna? Meaning, it's
very nice that you want a higher level of proof, but it's
not always available. And in a lot of places the only evidence
is that the guy gets called up for כהן. Kohen, Right? Now
of course the question is, why isn't there also the evidence about
נשיאת כפיים? Nesiat Kapayim. Right? Because presumably everybody there did, like the
ספרדים Sefardim do nowadays that we don't, is that they did a
daily נשיאת כפיים. So it's a so you know, it's interesting that
there's like a level between עלייה aliyah and תרומה, Terumah. which is
נשיאת כפיים. But anyway, that was his pushback. רבי אלעזר Rabbi Elazar
said, "ריש לקיש, Reish Lakish, it's nice you want that higher level
of proof, but that's unrealistic. You're going to say that if there's
no you know, if this isn't an agricultural town or whatever, that
you can't assume anybody's a כהן?" Kohen One minute. So,
okay, so זמנין, zimnin, now we don't know what the end of
that story was. But another time, הוה יתבי קמיה דרבי יוחנן. hava
yasvei kamei de'Rabbi Yochanan. רבי אלעזר Rabbi Elazar and ריש לקיש Reish
Lakish were sitting in front of רבי יוחנן. Rabbi Yochanan. Okay? אתא
כי ההוא מעשה לקמיה, ata ki hahu ma'aseh lekamei, an exact same
type of story came. Somebody testified about a guy that he got
the first עלייה, aliyah, that he was a
כהן. Kohen, And ריש לקיש Reish Lakish was the one that testified
about him. And ריש לקיש Reish Lakish says, "ראיתי שחלק על..." ra'iti
she'chilek al... sorry. One minute.
Somebody else testified about a guy got a first עלייה, aliyah, came
to רבי יוחנן, Rabbi Yochanan, said he's a כהן. Kohen, And then
ריש לקיש Reish Lakish said to this guy who was coming in
and saying I saw him get a first עלייה, aliyah, אמר ליה
ריש לקיש, amar lei Reish Lakish, "ראית שחלק על הגורן? ra'ita she'chilek
al hagoren? But did you ever see him get תרומה?" Truma So
ריש לקיש Reish Lakish is sticking by his position, which is that,
"I need to see him get תרומה Truma before I'm willing to
assume anything." אמר ליה רבי יוחנן, Amar lei Rabbi Yochanan, so רבי
יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan said to ריש לקיש, Reish Lakish, "ואם אין שם
גורן בטלה כהונה? v'im ein sham goren batla kehuna? And if there's
no גורן, goren, are you going to tell me that there's no
כהונה?" Kehunah? So הדר חזייה לרבי אלעזר בבישות. hadar chazai le'Rabbi Elazar
b'bisha. So then ריש לקיש Reish Lakish gave a dirty look to
רבי אלעזר. Rabbi Elazar. Why? Because רבי אלעזר Rabbi Elazar and ריש
לקיש Reish Lakish were like students of רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan or
תלמיד חבר talmid chaver of רבי יוחנן. Rabbi Yochanan. So רבי אלעזר
Rabbi Elazar challenged ריש לקיש Reish Lakish with a line that's clear
that where did he get this line from? From רבי יוחנן. Rabbi
Yochanan. So basically ריש לקיש Reish Lakish was upset, he says, "If
you were going to push back on me at that other first
event, you should have told me that it wasn't your idea, רבי
יוחנן, Rabbi Yochanan, it was רבי יוחנן's Rabbi Yochanan point, and then
I would have been more receptive to it." Okay? So he gave
רבי אלעזר Rabbi Elazar a dirty look. And he said to him,
אמר, amar, and
so ריש לקיש Reish Lakish said to רבי אלעזר, Rabbi Elazar, שמעת
מילי דבר נפחא, shamata milei de'bar Nafcha, "You heard the words of
בר נפחא, bar Nafcha, which was a way of referring to רבי
יוחנן, Rabbi Yochanan, ולא אמרת לן משמיה?
velo
amarta lan mishmei?
And you didn't tell it to me in his name? You should
have told me that that was a רבי יוחנן, Rabbi Yochanan, that
רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan said, 'I'm not impressed by getting an עלייה,
aliyah, I need to see him get תרומה.'" Truma. Okay? So now,
I'm sorry, no, excuse me, ריש לקיש Reish Lakish was the one
who was not impressed that he... he got an עליה. Aliyah. רבי
יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan says, you know, you can't always insist on the
תרומה Truma. thing, there's not always תרומה Truma. that's available, you know,
if there's no גורן, Goren, are you going to say there's no
כהונה? kehunah, So anyway, here you've got the idea that גמרא Gemara
introduce the idea that you go from an עליה Aliyah to assuming
he's a כהן Kohen. but that actually, even if it's not for
יוחסין Yuchsin purposes, actually is a big חידוש Chiddush because until now
we were talking about more weighty things, doing נשיאת כפים, Nesias Kapayim,
getting תרומה. Truma, So now we see that that actually is debated,
that ריש לקיש Reish Lakish actually says, I'm not impressed that he
got an עליה. Aliyah. I need to see something like תרומה. Truma
But רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan and then רבי אלעזר Rabbi Elazar who
got it from רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan and didn't say he got
it from רבי יוחנן, Rabbi Yochanan, pushes back and says, you can't
always insist on תרומה. Truma, You're going to tell me that if
there's no granaries in this place that we can't make any presumptions?
So getting an עליה Aliyah is good enough. Of course, the fascinating
question that remains is, okay, good enough for what purposes, right? And
it seems like since we're also dealing with the demand of תרומה,
trumah so it seems like the purpose that we're left with is
יוחסין, Yuchsin, right? because if you got תרומה trumah, covered and you've
got, you know, so what's left to prove other than יוחסין, Yuchsin,
unless of course we mean חלל, Challal, right? where there's always that
funny option. Okay, but the fascinating thing is that this גמרא, Gemara,
while we were, you know, pulling our hair out about can you
go from נשיאת כפים Nesias Kapayim to יוחסין, Yuchsin, it sounds like
in this גמרא Gemara the מסקנא Maskana is that רבי יוחנן Rabbi
Yochanan is willing to accept, you know, just getting an עליה Aliyah
as evidence, and sounds like maybe even evidence for יוחסין, Yuchsin, which
is like really shocking. Yes.
So presumably this also in the place of no negative evidence, right?
If someone were to say, well, you know, with this whole discussion,
I saw he married a גרושה Gerusha or I saw him go
in בית הקברות, Beis Hakevaros, would that be good enough to like
knock down the
חזקה? Chazaka? Or do we say that, you know, maybe he doesn't
know, you know. He knows the כהן, Kohen. you know, he's willing
to get the first עליה, Aliyah,
he doesn't know anything about בית הקברות, Beis Hakevaros, he doesn't know
his family? I don't know, I don't know. I'm sure it has
to do with various, you know, realities and presumptions. I don't know.
I don't know. Yeah. I was going to point out, at first
I thought that ביש Bish was like he was embarrassed. No, no,
it's Aramaic. It's ביש Bish for bad, right?
He gave him an... Yeah, he gave him a... he gave him
a dirty look.
Okay fine, but
he was embarrassed
though, because
they have a note here saying because he wouldn't have said that
in front of רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan if he knew. He repeated
himself the mistake in front of רבי יוחנן. Rabbi Yochanan.
The words in Aramaic were for bad.
No,
no, ריש לקיש, Reish Lakish, it wasn't a mistake, I mean it
was ריש לקיש's Reish Lakish position. So the way רש"י Rashi says
is that ריש לקיש Reish Lakish says, the reason I didn't, I
kept my position, was because when you told me your critique back
then, I didn't realize it was from רבי יוחנן. Rabbi Yochanan. If
you had told me that it was רבי יוחנן's Rabbi Yochanan position
that he said that you don't need to see the distribution of
תרומה, trumah I would have reconsidered my position. Right.
But he was just saying that he was embarrassed because if
he had told him originally... Oh, then I wouldn't have said that
to רבי יוחנן. Rabbi Yochanan. I wouldn't have got רבי יוחנן Rabbi
Yochanan to push back at me, right. And now I had to
be embarrassed by רבי יוחנן. Rabbi Yochanan. Okay, but all right anyway,
so this is fascinating because if you would ask us like, how
do you know somebody's a כהן, Kohen, the first thing most of
us would say is, well, did he get an... what עליה Aliyah
did he get? And here we're seeing that רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan
is prepared to accept that, and maybe even for יוחסין, Yuchsin, which
would be shocking. The גמרא Gemara doesn't spell out for what purpose.
Okay, so let's take a look. The גמרא Gemara says like this.
רבי חייא
בר אבא... Rabbi Chiya bar Abba... רבי Rabbi and
רבי חייא. Rabbi Chiya. So now we have a debate of רבי
Rabbi and רבי חייא. Rabbi Chiya. חד
העלה בן על פי אביו, Chad hela ben al pi aviv, one
had a son being treated as a כהן Kohen, because the father
said he was a כהן, Kohen, לכהונה. Likehunah. Now of course if
the father's a כהן, kohein. of course we're going to presume the
son is a כהן. kohein. Now it's possible not, it's possible he's
a חלל Challal and a גרושה Gerusha and whatever, right. So the
point is though the פשט Pshat of the סוגיא Sugya is, is
that the father says, this is my son, and therefore
he's a
כהן. kohein No, no, and
that's what I did mean that. Okay, we know that the father's
a כהן, kohein okay, and if we know this is a son,
we don't need to trust the father, we just assume that he's
a כהן, kohein we assume that he's not a חלל. Challal. The
case is we don't know that this is his son and he
comes into town and he says, by the way everybody, let me
introduce you to my son, he's been living abroad for the last
few years, he's my son, he's a כהן, Kohen. we believe the
father. Okay. So חד העלה בן על פי אביו לכהונה וחד העלה
אח על פי אחיו ללויה. Chad hela ben al pi aviv likehunah
vechad hela ach al pi achiv lelevia. And it's a similar case,
and the other one trusted the, you know, accepted the testimony, hey
guys, this is my brother, he's visiting from out of town, he's
a לוי, Levi, give him מעשר. Maaser. Okay. So now we're having
about believing another person, direct testimony, but it's only עדות של אחד
Edus shel echad and it's עדות Edus of a קרוב, Karov, right?
So that's so there's now well there's two issues, it's a קרוב
Karov and it's עד אחד. Ed echad. So עד אחד Ed echad
could be better, it's a separate person, it's not your own activity.
But again, before it was the fact that implicitly the community was
accepting it, that you were doing certain activities that would have been
a violation. Here we're a different type of a genre, it's just
straight testimony and testimony of somebody that's a קרוב. Karov. Okay, so
let's take a look.
So and one did the father and son and one did the
brother. Okay, תסתיים רבי העלה בן על פי אביו. Tistayem Rabbi hela
ben al pi aviv. רבי Rebbi was the one that trusted a
son based on the testimony of the father לכהונה. Likehunah. דתניא, Detanya,
we taught a ברייתא. דתניא, detanya, we taught a ברייתא, הרי שבא
ואמר, harei she-ba ve-amar,
somebody comes and says, בני זה וכהן הוא, beni zeh ve-kohein hu,
this is my son and he's a כהן. Kohen. נאמן, ne'eman, he's
believed לאכילה בתרומה, le-achilah be-trumah, that he can have him now eat
תרומה trumah, and we'll give him תרומה, trumah ואינו נאמן להשיאו אשה,
ve-eino ne'eman le-hasi'o ishah, but not for יוחסין yuchsin purposes. דברי רבי,
divrei Rebbi, that's what רבי Rebbi says. So explicitly רבי Rebbi. says
we believe at least for the תרומה trumah level. אמר לו רבי
חייא, amar lo Rebbi Chiyya, as רבי חייא Rebbi Chiyya said back
to him, אם אתה מאמינו לאכילה בתרומה תאמינו להשיאו אשה. im attah
ma'amino le-achilah be-trumah ta'amino le-hasi'o ishah. Look, make up your mind. If
you're going to believe him for תרומה, trumah you should believe him
for marriage.
ואם אי אתה מאמינו להשיאו אשה לא תאמינו לאכול בתרומה. ve-im i
attah ma'amino le-hasi'o ishah lo ta'amino le-echol be-trumah. So he does not
seem to be buying in to this whole division that we've had
for the last two days, which is you can believe somebody at
the תרומה trumah level but not at the marriage level. Now תוספות
Tosafos has a whole discussion about why really רבי חייא Rebbi Chiyya
would buy into that division, but he just means that it's here
it's not a legitimate type of a division. I won't unpack the
תוספות Tosafos for you. Whatever, I won't unpack the תוספות Tosafos for
you, but at least at the surface it sounds like רבי חייא
Rebbi Chiyya doesn't believe you can have different levels, but תוספות Tosafos
says he does, but there's some, and he explains why specifically a
problem here.
Okay, you could have a guy eating תרומה trumah, and being able
to marry a גרושה. grushah.
No, no, we're not talking about allowing, no, no, no, so let
me again clarify. יוחסין yuchsin does not mean that we, that we
relieve the restrictions of a כהן. Kohen. יוחסין yuchsin means that we
believe he's enough of a כהן in order to allow him to
marry somebody that a normal non-כהן would not be allowed to... Right,
right.
No, no, it would be like a high level, like, you know,
it's very מיוחס meyuchas family will only marry כהנים, kohanim, okay? And
that's the point. So for... it does not mean that we... no,
no, it does not mean that we allow things, okay? It means
that we don't, right, we don't believe he's a כהן to allow
him to marry a מיוחס meyuchas families, okay? But, but obviously we
wouldn't let him do things that we know are violations for כהנים.
kohanim. Okay. Now, so that was רבי. Rebbi רבי Rebbi believes the
testimony of a father on the son at least for תרומה trumah
purposes. אמר לו, amar lo, so he said back to him, "no,
אני המאמינו לאכילה בתרומה, ani hama'amino le-achilah be-trumah, I will believe him
for תרומה trumah purposes. שבידו להאכילו בתרומה." she-beyado le-hachilo be-trumah. Is this
guy, the father, basically, he could go ahead, take his own תרומה,
trumah go home and give it to the guy that he's saying
is his son? So since if he wanted to he could feed
his son תרומה trumah anyway, I'm going to believe him when it
comes to תרומה trumah issues. So that's a new idea, a wrinkle.
It's not just תרומה trumah is a less weighty level, okay? It's
that no, actually, because... and again, we're dealing with this new concept,
עד אחד קרוב. eid echad karov. So he's saying here's why I
believe him. I know he's an עד אחד, eid echad, I know
he's a קרוב, karov, this, that, but if he wanted to he
could feed the guy תרומה trumah anyway. So I'm going to believe
him for תרומה trumah. purposes.
Okay. שבידו להאכילו בתרומה. she-beyado le-hachilo be-trumah. ואיני מאמינו להשיאו אשה, ve-eini
ma'amino le-hasi'o ishah, but I don't believe him in order to let
him marry a מיוחס meyuchas woman. שאין בידו להשיאו אשה, she-ein beyado
le-hasi'o ishah, because that's not something he could do on his own
if he wanted to. Okay. So you see that רבי Rebbi believed
the father for the son, and even though it's עד אחד eid
echad and קרוב karov whatever, he believed him only at the תרומה
Terumah level because at least תרומה was something that he could have
done all on his own even if we wouldn't believe him. תסתיים,
tistayem,
that's a good proof that that's what רבי Rebbi holds.
ומדרבי העלה בן על פי אביו לכהונה, u-mide-Rebbi helah ben al pi
aviv li-kehunah, if רבי Rebbi was willing to marry the son on
the testimony of the father for כהונה, רבי חייא העלה אח על
פי אחיו ללוייה. Rebbi Chiyya helah ach al pi achiv li-leviyah. It
must be that רבי חייא Rebbi Chiyya was the one that was
able to trust a brother, somebody say "this guy's my brother and
he's a לוי." Levi. So now let's just read one more line
about this. ורבי חייא מאי שנא בן דלא? ve-Rebbi Chiyya mai shna
ben dela? Now the גמרא Gemara is assuming, and תוספות Tosafos says
it's not clear why the גמרא Gemara assumes this, like maybe just
רבי Rebbi had one case and רבי חייא Rebbi Chiyya had the
other case. But the גמרא Gemara assumes that somehow there's a debate.
Well, certainly in that ברייתא we just quoted before, רבי חייא Rebbi
Chiyya pushed back on רבי Rebbi believing the son on the father.
So the גמרא Gemara is assuming רבי חייא Rebbi Chiyya pushes back
on רבי Rebbi and saying you either believe the whole thing or
believe nothing, which presumably means that רבי חייא Rebbi Chiyya would say
I wouldn't believe the father on the son at least. So why
would רבי חייא Rebbi Chiyya not believe the father on the son
and he'll believe one brother on the other brother? Right? He pushed
back on רבי Rebbe about the father and the son. Why doesn't
he have the same problem about brothers? So מאי שנא בן דלא
דקרוב הוא אצל אביו? mai shna ben dela de-karov hu eitzel aviv?
So the son not because he's a קרוב. karov. אח נמי קרוב
הוא אצל אחיו? ach nami karov hu eitzel achiv? So by a
brother also he's a קרוב, karov, so if you're not willing to
believe a guy that he's the father, don't believe somebody that he's
the brother. So let's just give it one more minute and read
the answer. משיח לפי תומו. mesi'ach lefi tumo. Yeah, you're right. For
רבי חייא Rebbi Chiyya it really isn't about father-son and brother-brother. It's
really about whether it's a formal testimony or just like the guy's
just... yeah, en passant. The guy's just סתם stam talking, and because
he's סתם stam talking, we... there's sometimes interestingly, sometimes interestingly, there's more
of a presumption that he's telling the truth when he's not conscious
of what the consequences are. Like if I'm coming to testify, "Hey
buddy, this is my son, I want you to give him תרומה.
Hey everybody, this is my brother, I want you to give him
מעשר." ma'aser. So maybe he knows what... he's thinking about the consequences
and maybe therefore he's lying. Of course you could say if he's
formally testifying he's more telling the truth. But maybe also if he's
very much consciously doing it he's thinking about the consequences and maybe
he has an ulterior motive. But if somebody's just סתם stam gossiping
and שמוזינג, shmoozing, we may... Maybe more presume that he's telling the
truth. So unless of course if somebody knows how to work the
system, that's how they'll get people to, but okay.
Like אבא בר
שמואל?
Abba
bar Shmuel? Right.
Alright, so let's take a look, let's just read the story. במסיח
לפי תומו. Bemesiach Lefi Tumo. כי הא דאמר רב יהודה אמר שמואל,
Ki ha de'amar Rav Yehuda amar Shmuel, like רב יהודה Rav Yehuda
said in the name of שמואל, Shmuel, מעשה באדם אחד שהיה מסיח
לפי תומו. Maaseh be'adam echad shehayah mesiach lefi tumo. There was a
person who was just talking like of in all innocence. It literally
means talking in all innocence. ואמר Ve'amar and said, זכורני, Zachurni, oh
I, I remembered כשאני תינוק, keshe'ani tinok, when I was a baby
or whatever, small child, ומורכב על כתפיו של אבא, umurkav al ktefav
shel Abba, I was taking a piggyback ride on my father's shoulders,
והוציאוני מבית הספר, vehotzi'uni mibeit hasefer, and they took me out of
חדר, Cheder, והפשיטוני את כתונתי, vehipshituni et ktunti, and they removed my,
my cloak, והטבילוני, vehitbiluni, and they dunked me in a מקוה, Mikveh,
לאכול בתרומה לערב, le'echol bitrumah la'erev, so we could have our תרומה
meal that night. So he explains this whole thing about how, yeah,
they would always take me to the מקוה Mikveh and so that
night I would have, you know, we would have the, the grain
that everybody had been giving my father. So maybe he didn't even
realize what it meant. Oh, do you know what that means? No,
what does it mean? It means you're a כהן. Oh, really? I
didn't know that.
Okay, so anyway, you have to be a כהן.
Right, but you have cases
like that. You have cases like that that people have no idea.
You know I saw the funniest thing when I visited the grave
of my grandfather, it had these hands and pictures or whatever. Okay,
so ורבי
חייא מסיים
בה. Verabi Chiya mesayem bah. And here we get רבי חייא Rabbi
Chiya himself. רבי חייא Rabbi Chiya concluded this by saying, as that
this was the end of the story, וחבריי בדילין ממני, vechaveirai bedilin
mimeni, and all of my, my friends would keep their distance from
me, והיו קורין אותי יוחנן אוכל חלות. Vehayu korin oti Yochanan Ochel
Chalot. Oh, don't get close to יוחנן, Yochanan, he's the holy חלה
eater, we have to keep our distance from him. Okay, and based
on that testimony, והעלוהו רבי לכהונה על פיו. ve'he'eluhu Rebbe likhunah al
piv. רבי Rebbe, allowed him to be considered to be a כהן.
So the funny testimony, רבי, everybody making
fun of him, beating him up, give him some reward? But these
days, you know,
we don't, we don't do this anyway,
right?
Right. Mostly not, mostly what's the big deal? You want to, you
want to go ahead and get the first עליה, Aliyah, געזונטערהייט. Gezunterheit.
You want to go ahead and have a problem...